Guide to the Durham County (N.C.) papers, circa 1895-1980s RL.10026
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Durham County (N.C.) papers
1870s-1996 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Durham County (N.C.)
RL.10026
12.5 Linear Feet
Durham county is a county in northeast central North Carolina. The county was formed in 1881. Collection materials are predominantly arranged in chronological order beginning in 1870. Within the chronology, decades are broken down by subject. Subjects include: activism, art, business, churches, clubs, courts, education, landmarks, minorities, politics, public works, publications, senior citizens, the Watts Hospital, women, YMCA/YWCA. Subject folders contain miscellaneous manuscripts and printed materials, including numerous leaflets, booklets, pamphlets, and maps.
Historical note
Durham county is a county in northeast central North Carolina. The county was formed in 1881.
Collection Overview
Collection materials are predominately arranged in chronological order beginning in 1870. Within the chronology, decades are broken down by subject. Subjects include: activism, art, business, churches, clubs, courts, education, landmarks, minorities, politics, public works, publications, senior citizens, the Watts Hospital, women, YMCA/YWCA. Subject folders contain miscellaneous manuscripts and printed materials, including numerous leaflets, booklets, pamphlets, and maps. Collection is heavy in Durham Arts Council and related Durham-area arts publications and materials, workers' rights campaigns and African American political mobility. Some parts of the collection are unprocessed. Finding aid represents present ordering of folders, box labels, and box order.
Provenance
The Durham County (N.C.) records were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library in multiple accessions starting in 1937.
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48-hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Durham County (N.C.); Durham (N.C.) -- History; Churches -- North Carolina; Civil rights movements -- North Carolina -- Durham; Prohibition -- North Carolina -- History -- 19th century; Durham (N.C.) -- Social conditions; Public Schools -- North Carolina -- Durham; Durham (N.C.) -- Social life and customs; Durham County (N.C.) -- Maps; North Carolina Mutual Life Insurance Company; Durham (N.C.) Committee on the Affairs of Black People; Watts Hospital (Durham, N.C.); North Carolina College at Durham; League of Women Voters of Durham (Durham, N.C.); Durham County (N.C.). Library; Southern Conservatory of Music (Durham, N.C.); Durham County (N.C.); Association for the Preservation of the Eno River Valley
- Durham County (N.C.) papers, 1870s-1996 and undated; 1
  - Parades, 1895-1910s (Box 1)
  - Performing Arts, 1895-1910s (Box 1)
  - Durham Country Club, 1895-1910s (Box 1)
  - Up-To-Date Club, 1895-1910s (Box 1)
  - Women, 1895-1910s (Box 1)
  - Churches, 1895-1910s (Box 1)
  - Business, 1895-1910s (Box 1)
  - General, 1895-1910s (Box 1)
  - 1900s, circa 1895-1910s (Box 1)
  - Schools, 1895-1910s (Box 1)
  - Historic Sites and Buildings, 1870s-1890s (Box 2)
  - 19th Century papers, 1870s-1890s (Box 3)
  - Proceedings of Central Prohibition Club of Durham, 1886-1892 (Box 3)
  - First Annual Report of Watts Hospital, 1895 (Box 3)
  - General, 1920s (Box 4)
  - Assessments, 1920s (Box 4)
  - Business, 1920s (Box 4)
  - Churches, 1920s (Box 4)
  - Durham Morning Herald, 1920s (Box 4)
  - Blackwell Literary Society Roll Book, 1923-1926 (Box 4)
  - Miscellaneous, 1920s (Box 5)
  - Southern Conservatory of Music, 1920s (Box 5)
  - Schools, 1920s (Box 5)
  - Telephone Directory, 1920s (Box 5)
  - YMCA, 1920s (Box 5)
  - Maplewood Cemetary, 1920s (Box 5)
  - Performing Arts, 1920s (Box 5)
  - Watts Hospital, 1920s (Box 5)
  - Watts High Lights, Vol. 8, 1936-1937 (Box 6)
  - Schools, 1930s (Box 6)
  - Churches, 1930s (Box 6)
  - North Carolina Mutual Life Insurance Company, 1930s (Box 6)
  - Government, 1930s (Box 6)
  - Library, 1930s (Box 6)
  - Juvenille Court, 1930s (Box 6)
  - General, 1930s (Box 6)
  - United Daughters of the Confederacy, 1930s (Box 6)
  - Women's Club, 1930s (Box 6)
  - YMCA, 1930s (Box 6)
  - Miscellaneous, 1930s (Box 6)
  - Deeds, 1930s (Box 6)
  - American Legion, 1930s (Box 6)
  - Chamber of Commerce, 1930s (Box 6)
  - Business, 1940s (Box 7)
  - U.S.S. Durham, 1940s (Box 7)
  - Tourist Club, 1940s (Box 7)
  - Politics, 1940s (Box 7)
  - World War II Homefront Effort, 1940s (Box 7)
  - Miscellaneous, 1940s (Box 7)
  - Schools, 1940s (Box 7)
  - Kiwanis Club, 1940s (Box 7)
  - General, 1940s (Box 7)
  - Churches, 1940s (Box 7)
  - Centennial, 1950s (Box 8)
  - General, 1950s (Box 8)
  - Railroads, 1950s (Box 8)
  - Allied Arts, 1950s (Box 8)
  - Kiwanis, 1950s (Box 8)
  - Community Chest, 1950s (Box 8)
  - Business, 1950s (Box 8)
  - Performing Arts, 1950s (Box 8)
  - Churches, 1950s (Box 8)
  - Research Triangle, 1950s (Box 8)
  - Rotary Club, 1950s (Box 8)
  - Schools, 1950s (Box 8)
  - Allied Arts, 1960s (Box 9)
  - American Association of University Women, 1960s (Box 9)
  - Business, 1960s (Box 9)
  - Charities, 1960s (Box 9)
  - Churches, 1960s (Box 9)
  - Department of Public Welfare, 1960s (Box 9)
  - Minorities, 1960s (Box 10)
  - Libraries, 1960s (Box 10)
  - League of Women Voters, 1960s (Box 10)
  - Hospitals, 1960s (Box 10)
  - Durham Liberal Alliance, 1960s (Box 10)
  - General, 1960s (Box 10)
  - Durham Alliance, 1960s (Box 10)
  - Council on Human Relations, 1960s (Box 10)
  - Durham County Citizens' Council, 1960s (Box 10)
  - Miscellaneous, 1960s (Box 10)
  - Miscellaneous, 1960s (Box 11)
  - Inauguration of Dr. Samuel Proctor Massey, Jr., 1964 (Box 11)
  - North Carolina College at Durham, 1960s (Box 11)
  - Operation Breakthrough, 1960s (Box 11)
  - North Carolina "Anvil", 1960s (Box 11)
  - North Carolina Mutual Life Insurance Company, 1960s (Box 11)
  - Performing Arts, 1960s (Box 12)
  - Red Cross, 1960s (Box 12)
  - Politics, 1960s (Box 12)
  - Research Triangle, 1960s (Box 12)
  - Rotary Club, 1960s (Box 12)
  - Schools, 1960s (Box 12)
  - Senior Citizens, 1960s (Box 12)
  - Taxes, 1960s (Box 12)
  - Unions, 1960s (Box 12)
  - United Organization for Community Improvements, 1960s (Box 12)
  - YMCA/YWCA, 1960s (Box 12)
  - "The Action", 1970s (Box 13)
  - Allied Arts/Durham Arts Council, 1970s (Box 13)
  - Durham Allied Arts Calendar of Events, 1970s (Box 13)
  - Animal Protection Society, 1970s (Box 13)
  - "Arterie", 1970s (Box 14)
  - Bicentennial (United States), 1970s (Box 14)
  - Business, 1970s (Box 14)
  - Durham Hotel-Motel, 1970s (Box 15)
  - Charities, 1970s (Box 15)
  - Churches, 1970s (Box 15)
  - Consolidated Government, 1970s (Box 15)
  - Courts, 1970s (Box 15)
  - General, 1970s (Box 15)
  - Durham Arts Council, 1970s (Box 15)
  - Durham Voters Alliance, 1970s (Box 16)
  - Durham Women's Club, 1970s (Box 16)
  - Edgemont Community Center, 1970s (Box 16)
  - Eno River Association, 1970s (Box 16)
  - Hospitals, 1970s (Box 17)
  - Minorities, 1970s (Box 17)
  - Museums, 1970s (Box 17)
  - Miscellaneous, 1970s (Box 17)
  - Masons, 1970s (Box 17)
  - Libraries, 1970s (Box 17)
  - "Joe's Bozart", 1970s (Box 17)
  - Housing, 1970s (Box 17)
  - North Carolina Public Interest Research Group (NC PIRG), 1970s (Box 18)
  - Neighborhoods, 1970s (Box 18)
  - North Carolina Anvil, 1970s (Box 18)
  - North Carolina Mutual Life Insurance Company, 1970s (Box 18)
  - Operation Breakthrough, 1970s (Box 18)
  - Orange Preservation Society, 1970s (Box 18)
  - Performing Arts, 1970s (Box 18)
  - Politics, 1970s (Box 18)
  - Political Action in Christ (PAX), 1970s (Box 18)
  - Real Estate, 1970s (Box 18)
  - Research Triangle, 1970s (Box 19)
  - Roads and Highways, 1970s (Box 19)
  - Schools, 1970s (Box 19)
  - Senior Citizens, 1970s (Box 19)
  - Stagville Preservation Center, 1970s (Box 19)
  - Taxes and Budgets, 1970s (Box 19)
  - Trinity Park, 1970s (Box 19)
  - Unions, 1970s (Box 19)
  - United Way, 1970s (Box 19)
  - Vietnam War, 1970s (Box 19)
  - YMCA/YWCA, 1970s (Box 19)
  - Business, 1980s (Box 20)
  - Carolina Action/ACORN, 1980s (Box 20)
  - Carolina Theater, 1980s (Box 20)
  - County Centennial, 1980s (Box 20)
  - Papers, unidentified and undated, 1920-1989 and undated (Box 21)
  - "Durham Report", 1985 (Box 22)
  - Durham Public Relations Book, 1981 (Box 22)
  - "Inventory of Edgemont and East Durham Early Textile Mill Villages", 1980 (Box 22)
  - Eno River Calendar, 1984 (Box 22)
  - "Durham Committee on the Affairs of Black People: 50th Anniversary" Program, 1985 (Box 22)
  - Durham Arts Council, 1980s (Box 22)
  - General, 1980s (Box 22)
  - Voters' Alliance, 1980s (Box 22)
  - Women's Club, 1980s (Box 22)
  - Eno River Association, 1980s (Box 22)
  - Hospitals, 1980s (Box 22)
  - Libraries, 1980s (Box 22)
  - Museums, 1980s (Box 22)
  - Brightleaf District Advertisements, 1996 (Box 23)
  - Neighborhoods, 1980s (Box 23)
  - People's Alliance Fund, Inc., 1980s (Box 23)
  - Performing Arts, 1980s (Box 23)
  - United Way, 1980s (Box 23)
  - Tourists' Club, 1980s (Box 23)
  - Senior Citizens, 1980s (Box 23)
  - Schools, 1980s (Box 23)
  - Politics, 1980s (Box 23)
  - Woman's Club, 1980s (Box 23)
  - YMCA/YWCA, 1980s (Box 23)
  - Eno River Calendars, 1972-1980 (Box 24)
  - Historical Preservation Society, undated (Box 24)
  - Durham Morning Herald, Centennial Edition, April 26, 1953 (Box 25)